and tens of millions more around the world, in Columbus, Georgia, in Cardiff, Wales, in Chongqing, China, in Chennai, India will leave their homes, they'll get in their cars or they'll take public transportation or they will carry themselves by foot, and they'll step into a room and sit down next to someone they don't know or maybe someone they do, and the lights will go down and they'll watch a movie. They'll watch movies about aliens or robots, or robot aliens or regular people. But they will all be movies about what it means to be human. Millions will feel awe or fear, millions will laugh and millions will cry. And then the lights will come back on, and they'll reemerge into the world they knew several hours prior. And millions of people will look at the world a little bit differently than they did when they went in. Like going to temple or a mosque or a church, or any other religious institution, movie-going is, in many ways, a sacred ritual. Repeated week after week after week. I'll be there this weekend, just like I was on most weekends between the years of 1996 and 1990, at the multiplex, near the shopping mall about five miles from my childhood home in Columbus, Georgia. The funny thing is that somewhere between then and now, I accidentally changed part of the conversation about which of those movies get made. So, the story actually begins in 2005, in an office high above Sunset Boulevard, where I was a junior executive at Leonardo DiCaprio's production company Appian Way. And for those of you who aren't familiar with how the film industry works, it basically means that I was one of a few people behind the person who produces the movie for the people behind and in front of the camera, whose names you will better recognize than mine. Essentially, you're an assistant movie producer who does the unglamorous work that goes into the creative aspect of producing a movie. You make lists of writers and directors and actors who might be right for movies that you want to will into existence; you meet with many of them and their representatives, hoping to curry favor for some future date. And you read, a lot. You read novels that might become movies, you read comic books that might become movies, you read articles that might become movies, you read scripts that might become movies. And you read scripts from writers that might write the adaptations of the novels, of the comic books, of the articles, and might rewrite the scripts that you're already working on. All this in the hope of finding the next big thing or the next big writer who can deliver something that can make you and your company the next big thing. So in 2005, I was a development executive at Leonardo's production company. I got a phone call from the representative of a screenwriter that began pretty much the way all of those conversations did: "I've got Leo's next movie." Now in this movie, that his client had written, Leo would play an oil industry lobbyist whose girlfriend, a local meteorologist, threatens to leave him because his work contributes to global warming. And this is a situation that's been brought to a head by the fact that there's a hurricane forming in the Atlantic that's threatening to do Maria-like damage from Maine to Myrtle Beach. Leo, very sad about this impending break up, does a little more research about the hurricane and discovers that in its path across the Atlantic, it will pass over a long-dormant, though now active volcano that will spew toxic ash into its eye that will presumably be whipped into some sort of chemical weapon that will destroy the world. (Laughter) It was at that point that I asked him, "So are you basically pitching me 'Leo versus the toxic superstorm that will destroy humanity?'" And he responded by saying, "Well, when you say it like that, it sounds ridiculous." And I'm embarrassed to admit that I had the guy send me the script, and I read 30 pages before I was sure that it was as bad as I thought it was. Now, "Superstorm" is certainly an extreme example, but it's also not an unusual one. And unfortunately, most scripts aren't as easy to dismiss as that one. For example, a comedy about a high school senior, who, when faced with an unplanned pregnancy, makes an unusual decision regarding her unborn child. That's obviously "Juno." Two hundred and thirty million at the worldwide box office, four Oscar nominations, one win. How about a Mumbai teen who grew up in the slums wants to become a contestant on the Indian version of "Who Wants To Be A Millionaire?"? That's an easy one -- "Slumdog Millionaire." Three hundred seventy-seven million worldwide, 10 Oscar nominations and eight wins. A chimpanzee tells his story of living with the legendary pop star Michael Jackson. Anyone? (Laughter) It's a trick question. But it is a script called "Bubbles," that is going to be directed by Taika Waititi, the director of "Thor: Ragnarok." So, a large part of your job as a development executive is to separate the "Superstorms" from the "Slumdog Millionaires," and slightly more generally, the writers who write "Superstorm" from the writers who can write "Slumdog Millionaire." And the easiest way to do this, obviously, is to read all of the scripts, but that's, frankly, impossible. A good rule of thumb is that the Writers Guild of America registers about 50,000 new pieces of material every year, and most of them are screenplays. Of those, a reasonable estimate is about 5,000 of them make it through various filters, agencies, management companies, screenplay compositions and the like, and are read by someone at the production company or major studio level. And they're trying to decide whether they can become one of the 300-and-dropping movies that are released by the major studios or their sub-brands each year. I've described it before as being a little bit like walking into a members-only bookstore where the entire inventory is just organized haphazardly, and every book has the same, nondescript cover. Your job is to enter that bookstore and not come back until you've found the best and most profitable books there. It's anarchic and gleefully opaque. And everyone has their method to address these problems. You know, most rely on the major agencies and they just assume that if there's great talent in the world, they've already found their way to the agencies, regardless of the structural barriers that actually exist to get into the agencies in the first place. Others also constantly compare notes among themselves about what they've read and what's good, and they just hope that their cohort group is the best, most wired and has the best taste in town. And others try to read everything, but that's, again, impossible. If you're reading 500 screenplays in a year, you are reading a lot. And it's still only a small percentage of what's out there. Fundamentally, it's triage. And when you're in triage, you tend to default to conventional wisdom about what works and what doesn't. That a comedy about a young woman dealing with reproductive reality can't sell. That the story of an Indian teenager isn't viable in the domestic marketplace or anywhere else in the world outside of India. That the only source of viable movies is a very narrow groups of writers who have already found their way to living and working in Hollywood, who already have the best representation in the business, and are writing a very narrow band of stories. And I'm somewhat embarrassed to admit, that that's where I found myself in 2005. Sitting in that office above Sunset Boulevard, staring down that metaphorical anonymized bookstore, and having read nothing but bad scripts for months. And I took this to mean one of two things: either A: I was not very good at my job, which was, ostensibly, finding good scripts, or B: reading bad scripts was the job. In which case, my mother's weekly phone calls, asking me if my law school entrance exam scores were still valid was something I should probably pay more attention to. What I also knew was that I was about to go on vacation for two weeks, and as bad as reading bad scripts is when it is your job, it's even more painful on vacation. So I had to do something. So late one night at my office, I made a list of everyone that I had had breakfast, lunch, dinner or drinks with that had jobs similar to mine, and I sent them an anonymous email. And I made a very simple request. Send me a list of up to 10 of your favorite screenplays that meet three criteria. One: you love the screenplay, two: the filmed version of that screenplay will not be in theaters by the end of that calendar year, and three: you found out about the screenplay this year. This was not an appeal for the scripts that would be the next great blockbuster, not an appeal for the scripts that will win the Academy Award, they didn't need to be scripts that their bosses loved or that their studio wanted to make. It was very simply an opportunity for people to speak their minds about what they loved, which, in this world, is increasingly rare. Now, almost all of the 75 people I emailed anonymously responded. And then two dozen other people actually emailed to participate to this anonymous email address, but I confirmed that they did in fact have the jobs they claimed to have. And I then compiled the votes into a spreadsheet, ran a pivot table, output it to PowerPoint, and the night before I left for vacation, I slapped a quasi subversive name on it and emailed it back from that anonymous email address to everyone who voted. The Black List. A tribute to those who lost their careers during the anti-communist hysteria of the 1940s and 50s, and a conscious inversion of the notion that black somehow had a negative connotation. After arriving in Mexico, I pulled out a chair by the pool, started reading these scripts and found, to my shock and joy, that most of them were actually quite good. Mission accomplished. What I didn't and couldn't have expected was what happened next. About a week into my time on vacation, I stopped by the hotel's business center to check my email. This was a pre-iPhone world, after all. And found that this list that I had created anonymously had been forwarded back to me several dozen times, at my personal email address. Everyone was sharing this list of scripts that everyone had said that they loved, reading them and then loving them themselves. And my first reaction, that I can't actually say here, but will describe it as fear, the idea of surveying people about their scripts was certainly not a novel or a genius one. Surely, there was some unwritten Hollywood rule of omertà that had guided people away from doing that before that I was simply too naive to understand, it being so early in my career. I was sure I was going to get fired, and so I decided that day that A: I would never tell anybody that I had done this, and B: I would never do it again. Then, six months later, something even more bizarre happened. I was in my office, on Sunset, and got a phone call from another writer's agent. The call began very similarly to the call about "Superstorm": "I've got Leo's next movie." Now, that's not the interesting part. The interesting part was the way the call ended. Because this agent then told me, and I quote, "Don't tell anybody, but I have it on really good authority this is going to be the number one script on next year's Black List." (Laughter) Yeah. Suffice it to say, I was dumbfounded. Here was an agent, using the Black List, this thing that I had made anonymously and decided to never make again, to sell his client to me. To suggest that the script had merit, based solely on the possibility of being included on a list of beloved screenplays. After the call ended, I sat in my office, sort of staring out the window, alternating between shock and general giddiness. And then I realized that this thing that I had created had a lot more value than just me finding good screenplays to read over the holidays. And so I did it again the next year -- and the "LA Times" had outed me as the person who had created it -- and the year after that, and the year after that -- I've done it every year since 2005. And the results have been fascinating, because, unapologetic lying aside, this agent was exactly right. This list was evidence, to many people, of a script's value, and that a great script had greater value that, I think, a lot of people had previously anticipated. Very quickly, the writers whose scripts were on that list started getting jobs, those scripts started getting made, and the scripts that got made were often the ones that violated the assumptions about what worked and what didn't. They were scripts like "Juno" and "Little Miss Sunshine" and "The Queen" and "The King's Speech" and "Spotlight." And yes, "Slumdog Millionaire." And even an upcoming movie about Michael Jackson's chimpanzee. Now, I think it's really important that I pause here for a second and say that I can't take credit for the success of any of those movies. I didn't write them, I didn't direct them, I didn't produce them, I didn't gaff them, I didn't make food and craft service -- we all know how important that is. The credit for those movies, the credit for that success, goes to the people who made the films. What I did was change the way people looked at them. Accidentally, I asked if the conventional wisdom was correct. And certainly, there are movies on that list that would have gotten made without the Black List, but there are many that definitely would not have. And at a minimum, we've catalyzed a lot of them into production, and I think that's worth noting. There have been about 1,000 screenplays on the Black List since its inception in 2005. About 325 have been produced. They've been nominated for 300 Academy Awards, they've won 50. Four of the last nine Best Pictures have gone to scripts from the Black List, and 10 of the last 20 screenplay Oscars have gone to scripts from the Black List. All told, they've made about 25 billion dollars in worldwide box office, which means that hundreds of millions of people have seen these films when they leave their homes, and sit next to someone they don't know and the lights go down. And that's to say nothing of post-theatrical environments like DVD, streaming and, let's be honest, illegal downloads. Five years ago today, October 15, my business partner and I doubled down on this notion that screenwriting talent was not where we expected to find it, and we launched a website that would allow anybody on earth who had written an English-language screenplay to upload their script, have it evaluated, and make it available to thousands of film-industry professionals. And I'm pleased to say, in the five years since its launch, we've largely proved that thesis. Hundreds of writers from across the world have found representation, have had their work optioned or sold. Seven have even seen their films made in the last three years, including the film "Nightingale," the story of a war veteran's psychological decline, in which David Oyelowo's face is the only one on screen for the film's 90-minute duration. It was nominated for a Golden Globe and two Emmy Awards. It's also kind of cool that more than a dozen writers who were discovered on the website have ended up on this end-of-year annual list, including two of the last three number one writers. Simply put, the conventional wisdom about screenwriting merit -- where it was and where it could be found, was wrong. And this is notable, because as I mentioned before, in the triage of finding movies to make and making them, there's a lot of relying on conventional wisdom. And that conventional wisdom, maybe, just maybe, might be wrong to even greater consequence. Films about black people don't sell overseas. Female-driven action movies don't work, because women will see themselves in men, but men won't see themselves in women. That no one wants to see movies about women over 40. That our onscreen heroes have to conform to a very narrow idea about beauty that we consider conventional. What does that mean when those images are projected 30 feet high and the lights go down, for a kid that looks like me in Columbus, Georgia? Or a Muslim girl in Cardiff, Wales? Or a gay kid in Chennai? What does it mean for how we see ourselves and how we see the world and for how the world sees us? We live in very strange times. And I think for the most part, we all live in a state of constant triage. There's just too much information, too much stuff to contend with. And so as a rule, we tend to default to conventional wisdom. And I think it's important that we ask ourselves, constantly, how much of that conventional wisdom is all convention and no wisdom? And at what cost? Thank you. (Applause)
y cientos de miles más en todo el mundo, en Columbus, Georgia, en Cardiff, Gales, en Chongqing, China, en Madrás, India, saldrán de sus casas, se subirán a sus autos o usarán el transporte público o irán a pie, entrarán en una sala, se sentarán junto a alguien que no conocen, o quizás si lo conozcan, se apagarán las luces y verán una película. Verán películas sobre aliens o robots o aliens robots o gente normal. Pero todas serán películas sobre qué significa ser humano. Millones sentirán asombro o miedo, millones se reirán y millones llorarán. Y luego las luces volverán a encenderse y volverán al mundo que conocían hacía unas horas. Y millones de personas verán el mundo un poco distinto de como lo hacían cuando entraron. Como ir al templo o a la mezquita o a la iglesia, o a cualquier otra institución religiosa, ir al cine, de muchas maneras, es un ritual sagrado. Que se repite semana tras semana tras semana. Yo iré este fin de semana, igual que hecho casi todos los fines de semanas entre 1996 y 1990, al multicine, cerca del centro comercial a unos 8 km. de la casa de mi infancia en Columbus, Georgia. Lo curioso es que en algún momento entre entonces y ahora cambié accidentalmente parte de la conversación sobre cuáles de esas películas se llegan a hacer. La historia comienza en 2005, en un despacho en lo alto de Sunset Boulevard, donde era un joven ejecutivo en Appian Way, la productora de Leonardo DiCaprio. Y para aquellos que no sepan cómo funciona la industria del cine, básicamente significa que yo era uno de las pocos detrás de la persona que produce la película para la gente que está detrás y delante de la cámara y cuyos nombres reconocerán mejor que el mío. Era el ayudante del productor que hace el trabajo poco glamuroso que conlleva el aspecto creativo de producir una película. Se hacen listas de guionistas, directores y actores que pueden ser adecuados para las películas que quieren hacer; se reúnen con muchos de ellos y sus representantes, deseando ganarse su favor para una futura cita. Y leen mucho. Leen novelas que pueden convertirse en películas, cómics que pueden convertirse en películas, artículos que pueden convertirse en películas, guiones que pueden convertirse en películas. Y leen guiones de escritores que puede que escriban la adaptación de las novelas, los cómics, los artículos, y que puede que reescriban los guiones con los que ya trabajan. Todo con el fin de encontrar el próximo bombazo o al próximo gran guionista que pueda ofrecer algo que haga que Uds. o su empresa sean los próximos bombazos. En 2005 yo era ejecutivo de desarrollo en la productora de Leonardo. Recibí una llamada del representante de un guionista que empezó casi igual que todo ese tipo de conversaciones: "Tengo la próxima película de Leo". En la película que su cliente había escrito, Leo interpretaría a un miembro de la industria del petróleo cuya novia, una meteoróloga local, amenaza con dejarle porque su trabajo contribuye al calentamiento global. Y está situación es relevante porque hay un huracán en el Atlántico que amenaza con causar un daño similar al de Maria desde Maine hasta Myrtle Beach. Leo, muy triste por la posible ruptura, investiga un poco sobre el huracán y descubre que en su camino sobre el Atlántico, pasará por un volcán que lleva tiempo inactivo pero que ahora está activo y que lanzará ceniza tóxica al ojo del huracán lo que lo convertirá en un tipo de arma química que destruirá el mundo. (Risas) Llegados a ese punto le pregunté: "¿Me estás intentando colar 'Leo contra la supertormenta tóxica que destruirá la humanidad?'" Y como respuesta me dijo: "Bueno, si lo dices así suena ridículo". Y me avergüenza admitir que le permití que me enviara el guion y que leí 30 páginas para asegurarme de que era tan malo como pensaba. "Supertormenta" es un ejemplo extremo pero tampoco es un ejemplo infrecuente. Y desgraciadamente no todos los guiones se rechazan con tanta facilidad. Por ejemplo, una comedia sobre una chica en el último curso de instituto que al enfrentarse a un embarazo no deseado toma una decisión inusual respecto a su futuro hijo. Claramente es "Juno". USD 230 millones en la taquilla mundial, cuatro nominaciones a los Oscars, una victoria. ¿Y qué hay del adolescente de Bombay que creció entre chabolas y que quiere participar en la versión india de "¿Quién quiere ser millonario?"? Esa es fácil, "Slumdog Millionaire". USD 377 millones en todo el mundo, 10 nominaciones a los Oscars y 8 victorias. Un chimpacé cuenta la historia de su vida viviendo con el legendario Michael Jackson. ¿Alguien? (Risas) Es una pregunta trampa. Pero es un guion llamado "Bubbles" y va a ser dirigido por Taika Waititi, el director de "Thor: Ragnarok". Una gran parte del trabajo del ejecutivo de desarrollo es separar las "Supertormentas" de los "Slumdog Millionaires", y de manera más general los guionistas que escriben "Supertormenta" de los que escriben "Slumdog Millionaire". Y obviamente la manera más fácil de hacerlo es leyendo todos los guiones pero francamente, es imposible. Como regla general, el Sindicato de Guionistas de EE.UU. registra unas 50 000 piezas de material cada año y la mayoría son guiones. De estos, unos 5000 aproximadamente pasan varios filtros, agencias, empresas de gestión, composición de guiones y similares y los lee alguien de la productora o de algún gran estudio. Y se intenta decidir si pueden ser una de las 300, y bajando, películas que hacen los grandes estudios o algunos de sus asociados cada año. Alguna vez lo he descrito como entrar a una librería exclusiva para miembros en la que todo el inventario está organizado de cualquier manera y todos los libros tienen la misma portada sin descripción. El trabajo consiste en entrar a esa librería y no salir hasta que se encuentren los libros mejores y más rentables. Es anárquico y alegremente opaco. Y todos tienen un método para afrontar estos problemas. La mayoría confía en las grandes agencias y asumen que si hay un gran talento en el mundo, ya ha encontrado la forma de llegar a las agencias, sin importar las barreras estructurales que existan para llegar hasta las agencias en primer lugar. Otros están constantemente comparando notas entre ellos sobre lo que han leído y lo que es bueno y simplemente esperan que su séquito sea el mejor y más conectado y tenga el mejor gusto en la ciudad. Y otros tratan de leer todo pero una vez más, es imposible. Si leen 500 guiones al año están leyendo mucho. Y sigue siendo un pequeño porcentaje de lo que hay. Básicamente se usa el triaje. Y cuando se usa el triaje se tiende a caer en la sabiduría convencional sobre lo que funciona y lo que no. Una comedia sobre una mujer joven que lidia con la realidad reproductiva no vende. La historia de un adolescente indio no es viable en el mercado doméstico o en cualquier otro sitio fuera de India. La única fuente de películas viables es un grupo muy reducido de guionistas que ya se han hecho un hueco en Hollywood, que ya tienen los mejores representantes del negocio y que escriben una franja de historias muy limitada. Y me da un poco de vergüenza admitir que ahí es donde yo me encontraba en 2005. Sentado en el despacho sobre Sunset Boulevard, mirando a esa librería anónima y metafórica y habiendo leído guiones malos durante meses. Y pensé que eso significaba dos cosas: que A: no era muy bueno en mi trabajo, que aparentemente era encontrar buenos guiones, o B: leer guiones malos era mi trabajo. Por eso las llamadas semanales de mi madre preguntando si mi examen de acceso a la facultad de derecho seguía valiendo era algo a lo que debía prestar más atención. Lo que también sabía era que estaba a punto de irme de vacaciones y si leer malos guiones es malo cuando es tu trabajo, cuando estás de vacaciones es aún peor. Así que tenía que hacer algo. Una noche en mi despacho hice una lista de todos con quienes había desayunado, comido, cenado o tomado algo y que tenían trabajos parecidos al mío y les envié un email anónimo. Y les hice una petición muy simple. Envíenme una lista de hasta 10 de sus guiones preferidos que cumplan tres requisitos. Uno: el guion les encanta, dos: la versión cinematográfica del guion no estará en los cines al final de ese año natural, y tres: descubrieron ese guion este año. Esto no era un llamada para guiones que fueran a ser los siguientes blockbusters, ni una llamada para los que fueran a ganar el Oscar, no tenían por qué ser guiones que sus jefes amaran o que quisiera hacer el estudio. Era solo una oportunidad para que la gente diera su opinión sobre lo que les gustaba, que, en este mundo, es cada vez más raro. Casi todas las 75 personas a las que escribí de manera anónima respondieron. Y luego otras dos docenas de personas escribieron al email anónimo para poder participar, pero confirmé que de verdad tuvieran los trabajos que decían tener. Pasé los votos a una hoja de cálculo, hice una tabla cruzada, lo exporté a PowerPoint y la noche antes de irme de vacaciones le puse un nombre casi subversivo y se lo envié desde el email anónimo a todos los que votaron. La lista "negra". Un homenaje a los que perdieron sus carreras con la histeria anticomunista de los años 40 y 50 y una inversión consciente de la noción de que de alguna manera negro tiene una connotación negativa. Tras llegar a México, llevé una silla hasta la piscina, empecé a leer los guiones y descubrí, para mi sorpresa y alegría, que la gran mayoría eran bastante buenos. Misión cumplida. Lo que no hube esperado es lo que pasó después. Cuando llevaba cerca de una semana de vacaciones pasé por el centro de negocios del hotel para mirar mi email. Después de todo ese era un mundo pre iPhone. Y descubrí que la lista que había creado de manera anónima me la habían reenviado varias docenas de veces a mi email personal. Todo el mundo estaba compartiendo la lista de guiones que todos amaban, leyéndolos y amándolos ellos también. Y mi primera reacción, que en realidad no puedo decir aquí, pero que la describiré como miedo, la idea de tantear a la gente sobre los guiones no era ni nueva ni ingeniosa. Seguro que había alguna ley del silencio no escrita en Hollywood que había evitado que la gente lo intentara antes y sobre la que yo era demasiado ingenuo para conocerla, pues estaba en el principio de mi carrera. Estaba seguro de que me iban a despedir así que ese día decidí que A: no contaría a nadie que lo había hecho, y B: nunca lo volvería a hacer. Seis meses después pasó algo todavía más extraño. Estaba en mi despacho, en Sunset, y recibí una llamada del agente de otro guionista. La llamada comenzó de manera muy similar a la llamada de "Supertormenta": "Tengo la próxima película de Leo". Esa no es la parte interesante. Lo interesante fue la forma en que acabó la llamada. Porque ese agente me dijo, y cito literal, "No se lo digas a nadie pero sé de buena mano que va a ser el guion número uno en la Lista negra del año que viene". (Risas) Sí. No hace falta decir que me quedé a cuadros. Tenía a una agente usando la Lista negra, que yo había hecho anónimamente, y que decidí no volver a hacer, para venderme a su cliente. Sugirió que el guion tenía mérito basándose solo en la posibilidad de ser incluído en la lista de guiones amados. Cuando acabó la llamada me senté en mi despacho y miré por la ventana, entre el shock y el vértigo. Y entonces me di cuenta de que eso que había creado tenía mucho más valor que el que yo encontrara buenos guiones para leer en vacaciones. Así que lo hice otra vez el año siguiente, y el "LA Times" me destapó como la persona que la había creado, y el año siguiente, y el año siguiente... lo he hecho todos los años desde 2005. Y los resultados han sido fascinantes, porque, mentiras descaradas aparte, ese agente tenía toda la razón. Para mucha gente, la lista era la prueba del valor del guion y de que un guion tenía más valor de lo que mucha gente, pienso, había anticipado. Rápidamente, los escritores cuyos guiones estaban en la lista empezaron a conseguir trabajos, esos guiones empezaron a hacerse y los guiones que se hacían a menudo eran los que violaban las suposiciones sobre lo que funcionaba y lo que no. Había guiones como "Juno" y "Pequeña Miss Sunshine" y "The Queen" y "El discurso del rey" y "Spotlight". Y sí, "Slumdog Millionaire" E incluso una película próxima sobre el chimancé de Michael Jackson. Creo que es muy importante que haga una pausa aquí un momento para decir que el éxito de ninguna de esas películas es mérito mío. Yo no las escribí, no las dirigí, no las produje, no las iluminé, no preparé la comida ni el catering... todos sabemos lo importante que es eso. El crédito de esas películas, el crédito de ese éxito, es de la gente que hizo las películas. Yo lo que hice fue cambiar la forma en la que la gente las veía. Accidentalmente pregunté si la sabiduría convencional era correcta. Y obviamente hay películas en esa lista que se habrían hecho sin la Lista negra, pero hay muchas que desde luego no. Como mínimo, hemos catalizado que se lleven a producción y creo que es digno de mencionar. Ha habido unos 1000 guiones en la Lista negra desde que se descubrió en 2005. Unos 325 han sido producidos. Han sido nominados a 300 Oscars, han ganado 50. 4 de las últimas 9 ediciones de "Mejores películas" fueron para guiones de la Lista negra y 10 de los últimos 20 Oscars de guiones han ido a guiones de la Lista negra. Han recaudado USD 25 mil millones en la taquilla mundial, lo que significa que cientos de millones de personas han visto estas películas fuera de sus casas, se han sentado junto a alguien desconocido y se han apagado las luces. Y eso sin decir nada de los entornos fuera del cine, como el DVD, el streaming y, honestamente, las descargas ilegales. Hace hoy cinco años, el 15 de octubre, mi socio y yo reforzamos la idea de que no ibamos a encontrar el talento de los guionistas donde pensábamos y lanzamos una web que permitía que cualquier persona del mundo que hubiera escrito un guion en inglés lo subiera, fuera evaluado y lo pusiera a disposición de miles de profesionales de la industria. Y me alegra decir que en los cinco años desde que existe hemos demostrado esa tesis con creces. Cientos de escritores en el mundo han encontrado representantes, han opcionado o vendido su trabajo. 7 se han convertido en películas en los últimos 3 años, incluyendo "Nightingale", la historia del declive psicológico de un veterano, en la que la cara de David Oyelowo es la única en pantalla durante los 90 minutos que dura. Fue nominada a un Globo de Oro y a dos premios Emmy. También es genial que más de una docena de escritores que fueron descubiertos en la web han acabado en esta lista anual, incluídos dos de los últimos tres escritores número uno. Sencillamente, la sabiduría convencional sobre la calidad de los guiones, dónde está y dónde se podía encontrar, estaba equivocada. Y esto es notable porque, como mencioné antes, en el triaje de encontrar películas para hacer y hacerlas, se confía mucho en la sabiduría convencional. Y esa sabiduría convencional, quizás y solo quizás pueden estar equivocada con mayores consecuencias. Las películas sobre negros no se venden en el extranjero. Las películas de acción sobre mujeres no funcionan porque las mujeres se verán en los hombres pero los hombres en las mujeres no. Que nadie quiere ver películas sobre mujeres de más de 40 años. Que nuestros héroes del cine tienen que ajustarse a una idea de belleza limitada que consideramos convencional. ¿Qué significa cuando esas imágenes se proyectan a 9 metros de alto y se apagan las luces, para niños con mi aspecto en Columbus, Georgia? ¿O una niña musulmana en Cardiff, Gales? ¿O un niño gay en Madrás? ¿Qué dice de cómo nos vemos a nosotros mismos, o de cómo vemos el mundo o cómo el mundo nos ve a nosotros? Vivimos en un tiempo muy extraño. Y creo que en la mayor parte vivimos en un estado de triaje constante. Hay demasiada información, demasiadas cosas contra las que pelear. Y como norma, tendemos a usar la sabiduría convencional. Y creo que es importante que nos preguntemos constantemente ¿cuánto de esa sabiduría convencional es convención y no sabiduría? ¿Y a qué precio? Gracias. (Aplausos)